Okay, טוב *tov*. Today's דף *daf* is צדי ו"ו *tzadi vav*, 96,
which, so, we, and we pick up at the very top. It's
a short דף *daf*. We had been just discussing this issue about
first of all understanding when the Torah says that if you cook
a חטאת chatas *chatas* and we're going to expand this to other
קרבנות korbanot *korbanos* in a pottery vessel, you break it; and if
it's in a metal vessel, you like scald it and rinse it.
And the question was, is it about whether the vessel absorbs the
taste, בליעה blia, *bliah*, or whether it was cooked in it? So
we had the case about pouring boiling hot stew from a different
pot into that, which is assumed to be not בישול *bishul*, which
is important, the idea that עירוי *iruy* is not בישול *bishul*, but
it does get absorbed, it is בליעה *bliah*. So it might be
that for, I mean, again, there's a way to read it that
it doesn't mean it's not בישול *bishul* in this vessel, but it
does achieve בישול *bishul*. But reading it in the simplest sense, it's
not בישול *bishul*, so that's relevant for things like שבת *Shabbos*, for
things like בשר בחלב *basar b'chalav*. But it is בליעה *bliah*, so
that's relevant for like כשרות kashrus, *kashrus*, that stuff would get absorbed
through עירוי *iruy*. Anyway, that's that case, and we asked, what about
the reverse case? Something that was suspended in it, but that wasn't
actually touch the walls, which is your classic oven. And the גמרא
Gemorah *Gemara*'s assumption, interesting for discussions about ovens, is that there's no
בליעה *bliah*, there's no absorption, but there is בישול *bishul*. And we
didn't resolve that question. Okay, so that's that issue about the pot,
and then it led the גמרא Gemorah *Gemara* to a discussion
about if you actually cook something in a pottery oven, that actually
you can כשר kashering *kasher* the oven, even if it's made out
of what do you call it, even if it's made out of,
you know, pottery, חרס cheres, *cheres*, by,
by putting a fire in it and by burning it out, so
that there is a way to כשר kasher *kasher* pottery. So the
גמרא Gemorah *Gemara* then asked, so then why isn't there always a
way to כשר kashering. *kasher* pottery? And the answer is, well, because
you have to have the fire on the inside, not on the
outside, and you could try to do that by a normal pot,
pottery pot, ceramic pot, but you would be afraid you would break
it, and we wouldn't trust you to do the job. But in
an oven, when you do the fire on the inside, that really
is a way to כשר kashering *kasher* pottery. One minute. So now
the גמרא Gemorah *Gemara*'s going to have a question, which is then
why does the Torah say when you cook something, a חטאת chatas,
*chatas* or whatever, in like a ceramic, in a pottery pot, you
have to break it? Why don't you just כשר kashering *kasher* it
if you're really telling me there is a way to כשר kasher,
*kasher*? Okay, question in a minute, but let's just finish that thought,
top of צדי ו"ו עמוד א' *tzadi vav amud aleph*. אלא Ella
*Ela*, says the גמרא Gemorah *Gemara*, if that's true, קדירות של מקדש
Mikdash, אמאי ישברו *kideiras shel mikdash amai yishavru*? Why does the Torah
say your pottery pots, break them? נהדרינהו לכבשונות *Nahadreinu l'kivshonos*?
Put them back into the kilns? That was the question I was
going to ask. Excellent, see that. So it might be true that
we won't normally, like, rabbinically we'll say we don't want you to
כשר kasher *kasher* that way, we're afraid that you won't, you know,
put the fire hot enough on the inside and that you'll try
to protect it and you won't do a good job. We get
that, all of that is a rabbinic protection. Okay, but
from the Torah's perspective, where there aren't these rabbinic protections, why was
the Torah said that the only option is to break it? You're
telling me that if you really completely put a fire on the
inside of it, it's a way of כשר kashering. *kashering* it. So
why is that not an option in the Torah? Okay, is this
really true you can כשר kashering *kasher* pottery this way? So the
גמרא Gemorah *Gemara* says, you know what, in principle it is, but
here's why we don't do it.
Actually, I misframed the question. The question isn't why did the Torah
say? תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* sort of asks that question. The question is,
why in practice? We'll get why the Torah doesn't say in a
minute. But why in practice did they not כשר kashering *kasher* the
pottery vessels in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash. *Beis Hamikdash*? Why didn't
they just, you know, maybe you could trust the כהנים *Kohanim* and
so on? Why in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* in practice did
they break it? Why didn't they just put them back into the
kilns? And the answer is, so אמר רב זירא *Amar Rav Zeira*,
לפי שאין עושים כבשונות בירושלים *l'fi she'ein osim kivshonos b'Yerushalayim*, because you
don't make kilns in ירושלים Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*, they create a tremendous amount
of smoke, we're very protective about the air quality in ירושלים Yerushalayim
*Yerushalayim*, etc. And therefore, in practice, you're right, if you waive the
rabbinic restrictions, you can כשר kasher *kasher* pottery by putting it back
in the kiln. Rabbis didn't let you do it, they didn't trust
you. And the reason they didn't do it in the בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* was just because that there were no kilns in ירושלים
Yerushalayim. *Yerushalayim*. Okay, now two important things. One is the question that
I asked a minute ago, that answers in practice why they didn't
do it in the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, but it doesn't say
why the Torah didn't say to do it. Okay, so we'll get
back to that in a second. The other point that I want
to make is the question about, who ever told you that it
is sufficient to כשר kashering. *kasher*? Meaning the Torah gives you a
ritual to do when you cook this stuff in it, right? You
either scald it and rinse it by a metal vessel, or you
go ahead and you break it by a pottery vessel. What makes,
even if we'll assume, right, that the גמרא Gemorah *Gemara*'s assuming now
that you can כשר kashering *kasher* pottery vessels by restoring them to
their kiln and by putting a fire inside them or whatever, whoever
said that the Torah said it's enough to כשר kasher *kasher* the
vessel? We're going to find... out in a minute for example that
you know if you scald a metal vessel that's enough to כשר
kasher it, but that's not enough from the תורה, Torah, the תורה's
Torah a ritual. You scalded it and then you rinsed it. Okay,
so maybe who says כשר kasher really suffices here? Why does the
גמרא Gemorah assume just because you could כשר kashering it it solves
the problem? So you got the question? So רש״י Rashi says that
he assumes that the גמרא Gemorah had concluded its question before and
that the conclusion of the גמרא Gemara before was that it really
is just about absorption and that if you cooked something inside without
it being absorbed, without it touching the walls, it would not have
the הלכה halacha that you would have to scald it or break
it or whatever. That really the whole הלכה halacha is when it
absorbs. So רש״י Rashi actually says that based on the earlier discussion,
yes, at the end of the day it is really about כשר.
kashering, So why the תורה Torah also says you've got to rinse
when it's metal, who knows? If that's the way you're כשר kasher
it, then maybe the תורה Torah added this extra ritual of rinsing
it. But at the core, since it's about בליעה, this requires the
process of either shattering or scalding, this does not. So therefore it
really is about כשר kasher and if you could find another way
to כשר, kashering like returning it into the kiln, that would suffice.
And that's why the גמרא's Gemara saying, so why not just כשר
kashering the pottery vessel? תוספות Tosfos has two different answers to that.
One is תוספות Tosfos, is not prepared to say that we've concluded
this question. And it could be that cooking without absorption actually does
require the same process. So it's not really all about absorbing. And
therefore it shouldn't all be about כשר. kashering Nevertheless, says תוספות, Tosfos
we are going to assume that even if this case is included,
it's only included because רש״י Rashi is basically right. The conceptual model
is absorbed. The vessel absorbed and therefore you got to do something,
scald it, break it, etc. Okay, but included in the absorbed, like
you know like we sometimes say שומע כעונה, Shomeia Keoneh, if you
listen to a ברכה brocha it's like you said it. The model
still is saying it, but listening is like you said it. So
תוספות Tosfos says you know what? רש״י Rashi in principle is right.
It's fundamentally is about absorbing. Okay,
but we're going to include cooking without absorbing as if it were
absorbing. Okay, so still the, meaning I don't agree with you רש״י
Rashi that this case does not require the process, it might be
that this case does require the ritual. But I'll agree with you
that the model remains the model of absorbing and this case is
like it absorbed. Since the model remains that of absorbing, then in
the end yes I do agree with you רש״י Rashi that כשר
kashering, another way, that's why the גמרא's Gemara assuming that כשר kasher
another way like putting it back into the kiln actually would work.
So that's a variation of רש״י. Rashi. The גמרא Gemara says why
don't we just כשר kasher the pottery vessel? Which shows that fundamentally
it's about absorption and כשר. kashering It's just that תוספות Tosfos says
you don't have to say we פסקן pasken that this is no
good, that this is not required, this could be required but it's
still the model. Okay, of it. Now how do we know that's
the model? Maybe it's just סתם stam a ritual? Right? Whoever told
us that was the model?
Sound like it's a ritual?
It is a ritual. I know, but how do we know it's
a ritual that's based on an idea of כשר kasher and absorption?
So תוספות Tosfos says well, since the תורה Torah gives a different
ritual for pottery and for metal, the only logic for that different
ritual, breaking versus whatever, you know, versus scalding, it only makes sense
if the issue relates to whether the taste got absorbed into the
vessel, that stuff gets more absorbed into pottery and therefore it's harder
to get out, etc., etc. So we can infer from the different
treatment. And we're going to see later, right? One of the things
we learn from the whole way that you
כשר kasher metal is how do you כשר kashering. metal. And one
of the things we learn about the fact that you break the
pottery is that you can't כשר kashering, pottery. So at the end
of the day, the fact that there are these different rituals and
there are these different physical attributes of these two vessels, okay, we
infer that at the end of the day really it is about
a question of absorption. So that basically saying I agree with you
רש״י, Rashi, but I just want to include this case as well.
But in principle, given the difference of the rituals and the difference
of the material, it is about absorption and therefore the גמרא's Gemara,
saying if you come up with a new way which isn't the
תורה Torah ritual of breaking the pottery, if you really were to
come up with a new way of כשר kasher a pot like
putting it back in the kiln, in theory that could work. And
that's the גמרא's Gemara question. Okay, and then the גמרא's Gemara only
answer to that is okay but we don't have kilns in ירושלים.
Yerushalayim All right. תוספות Tosafot has a yet a third answer about
how putting it back in a kiln is like making it a
brand new vessel. It's like you know and therefore even if it's
not about כשר, kasher you've completely made it a new vessel and
therefore you don't have to go through this process of this ritual
because now you have like a brand new pot. ירושלים Yerushalayim.
produced no pottery according?
Well yeah, you'd have to import it. Now the question is okay
now
here's though the next question. Why, that explains why they didn't do
it in the time of the בית המקדש. Okay, because they don't
want kilns in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. But now we're still left with the
question about but why did the תורה Torah say break it? Why
didn't the תורה Torah give me an option? of going ahead and
restoring it to a kiln. The תורה Torah doesn't have a גזרה
gezeirah I won't do a good job, and the תורה Torah didn't
have the principle that in ירושלים we don't have kilns. So why
didn't the תורה Torah at least allow that as an option of
restoring something to a kiln? That, you know, explains why they didn't
do it in practice, but why not allow it as an option?
So if you take a look at רש"י, Rashi, רש"י Rashi says
three lines from the top, וניהי דבמשכן כתיב ישבר לפי שלא היו
קבועים להיות להם כבשנות לצרף כלי חרס. V'nihi d'b'mishkan kesiv yishaver lefi
shelo hayu kevuim lihyos lahem kivshanos l'tzaref klei cheres. Okay, חרס, cheres,
חרס, cheres. what did I say? Okay, לצרף כלי חרס. l'tzaref klei
cheres. Okay, כסף kesef
I said, חרס. אבל במקדש נדנינו לפי כבשנות. Aval b'mikdash nadninu l'fey
kivshanos. So רש"י Rashi says, you know what, the תורה Torah didn't
say it either because you don't have kilns as you're walking through
the wilderness of סיני. Sinai. Okay, so that's רש"י's Rashi answer. It
wasn't in the פסוקים psukim because it wasn't relevant in the פסוקים
psukim either. All right. תוספות Tosafot has a different answer. תוספות's answer
is that actually, this is going to come as a surprise, but
once we've established what the idea is about absorption, the fact that
you break a pot is actually a leniency. Why is it a
leniency that you break a pot? The תורה's Torah telling you you're
even allowed to break a pot. You want to restore it to
a kiln? Be my guest. So why is it a leniency? You'd
think that that's being very strict, you're telling me you have to
destroy it. No, because if the whole point is to get the
taste out of the walls, when you break the pot, you haven't
gotten the taste out of the walls. So I might think that
breaking the pot, although it destroys the pot, maybe that's not sufficient.
Maybe the תורה Torah demands that I actually destroy the taste from
the world, I actually extract it from the world. Okay, so that
could explain why the תורה's Torah telling you you're even allowed to
break it, but you want to restore it to a kiln, be
my guest. Okay, so now where we are in the גמרא Gemara
is, we've established that in principle you can כשר kasher pottery by
making the fire on the inside, not on the outside or presumably
immersing it in fire, like doing a kiln. But the רבנן Rabbanim
don't trust you to כשר kashering pottery that way. It in theory
would be a way to deal with the stuff of the that
you cook a חטאת chatas, in and so on, because now we've
established that one way or another that implicitly these rituals in the
תורה Torah about the cooking of the קרבנות korbanos. are anchored in
an idea of כשר kasher and absorption, and therefore in theory restoring
it to a kiln would work for the pots in the מקדש,
Mikdash but we're just not going to do it because we don't
want kilns in ירושלים. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara's continues.
So, wait, but if it's really, so why is the תורה Torah
letting you breaking it then? I mean, it's not כשר kashering. it,
it's just ruining it.
Right? Okay, because at the end of the day, if you're not
going to use it, presumably that's fine, even though the taste remains
in the walls, if you're not going to use it, it's fine.
So then getting back to the same thing with the בגדי כהונה
Bigdei Kehunah that you're not going to use them anymore, why would
you need to launder them? Or are you saying that's just a
special thing by?
Yeah, I can't, I can't, I'm not, it's a good question, I'm
not, I can't assume that it's the same principle for both. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara's says like this: אמר אביי, Amar Abaye,
אביי Abaye says, וכי עושין אשפתות בעזרה? v'chi osin ashpatos b'azarah? So
אביי Abaye says, what do you mean? Oh, okay, we can't do
a kiln because we can't make kilns in ירושלים. Okay, you know
what else you shouldn't be doing? You shouldn't make, you shouldn't be
making garbage heaps in the עזרה. Azarah. But there you are, no,
you're just breaking pots in the עזרה. Azarah. Is that a nice
thing to do? To take all your pots and throw them on
the ground and have all these little shards there? That's also not
a nice thing, so as long, rather than make a lot of
shards in the עזרה, Azarah, why not make a little kiln? So
אשתמיטתיה, ishtamiteh, so he forgot, הא דתני, ha d'tani, that which we
taught, שמעיה, Shmaya, הא דתני שמעיה, ha d'tani Shmaya, that or רב
שמעיה, Rav Shmaya, because שמעיה Shmaya would be a little early, that
which רב שמעיה Rav Shmaya taught, בכלנבו, b'Kalanbo, בכלנבו's b'Kalanbo some place,
okay, what?
It's a city in בבל. Bavel.
City in בבל. Bavel. Okay, שברי כלי חרס נבלעים במקומן. shivrei klei
cheres nivlaim bimkoman. Ah, it was a miracle, when they broke the
pottery vessels, they got absorbed right there magically in the place. So
that's the answer to אביי's Abaye question. All right, anyway, you could
also just say also, you know, you break it and then you
sweep it away or something, who says you leave it there? Anyway,
it's still not as bad as having an ongoing kiln. Anyway, fine.
So that's our answer. Our answer is that at the end this
is rooted in an issue of absorption. כשר kasher through a kiln
would in theory be okay, but in practice it doesn't work out.
אלא fine, now the גמרא Gemara's says like this: אלא הא דאמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה תנור של מקדש של מתכת היה.
Ella ha d'amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha Tanur shel Mikdash
shel mateshes hayah. One minute, but we said yesterday that they had
a metal oven. Okay, and that led to our question about whether
if you suspended something, would it require כשר, kasher and we said,
well, not everything was suspended, there were the breads that weren't suspended.
Fine, but they had a metal oven. Presumably the reason they had
a metal oven was because
you don't want to start having to shatter your ovens every time
you use them.
But according to you, just put the fire back in the oven,
re-like do your, you know, self-cleaning oven, you know, fire it, you
know, fire it up, and that should be fine. So why not
use a pottery oven?
נעבדי דחרס דליסקו מבפנים. Na'avdei d'cheres d'lisko mibifnim. Why not do it
of pottery, since there you're putting the fire on the inside? You
don't need a kiln, which is like an immersion in fire, you
just have the fire on the inside. That's where this whole discussion
started, that if a fire's on the inside of an oven, it
can כשר kasher a pottery oven. So why didn't they have
a pottery oven?
Yeah, a kiln, you basically is like, you know, you've got a
raging fire and you put pottery inside of the kiln. Okay. And
you mean in terms of like the smoke and the pollution issue?
Yeah, I don't know what to say about that. But you need
an oven. Okay. So למעשה lemayseh *lema'aseh* they had an oven anyway.
Okay. And since the fire's on the inside, okay, so why don't
we just, what do you call it? So why don't, why not
a pottery oven should be fine? We'll כשר kasher *kasher* it. We
don't have to break it. So תימא *teima* it's choice? No, דכיון
דאיכא שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים דאפייתן בתנור וקדשתן בתנור *de'keivan de'ika shtei
halechem v'lechem hapanim de'afiyatan batanur v'kiddushan batanur*. No, no, no. Here's the
point. The point is you're right. In the terms of principles of
using the oven to cook a חטאת chatas *chatas* in or whatever,
wouldn't be a problem. You know, just turn it on for an
hour to the highest temperature, you're all ready for פסח Pesach *Pesach*,
you're all ready to use it for the next thing. No problem.
The reason was, it's not that we can't כשר kashering *kasher* it.
The reason was, was that there's certain breads that because they don't
have oil in it and you don't mix it in a כלי
kli, שרת *kli shareis* ahead of time, that the כלי kli, *kli*
their כלי שרת *kli shareis* is the oven itself. So the שתי
הלחם *shtei halechem* and the לחם הפנים *lechem hapanim* and also the
מנחת מאפה תנור *minchas ma'afeh tanur*, since they are baked in the
oven and קדשתן בתנור *kiddushan batanur*, that's where they become sanctified, הוי
ליה כלי שרת *havei lei kli shareis*. The oven for them is
the כלי שרת *kli shareis*. Okay. It's not that it's put in
some other vessel ahead of time that it's mixed with oil or
whatever. And כלי שרת *kli shareis* wait a minute, let me finish
my sentence. וכלי שרת דחרס לא עבדינן *v'kli shareis de'cheres lo avdinan*.
So we don't make a כלי שרת *kli shareis* out of pottery.
So in principle you're right. If we wanted to have an oven
designated for the cooking of of the meat sacrifices, then it would
not then we would not have it would be fine. And then
we would just fire it up and cleanse it out and we
wouldn't need to go through this ritual of breaking it or whatever.
The only reason we need a metal one is because we want
to be using the oven also as a כלי שרת *kli shareis*.
And there's a הלכה halacha? *halacha* that you don't make כלי שרת
*kli shareis* out of pottery. And if you just turn the page,
ואפילו רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה לא קאמר אלא דעץ *v'afilu Rabbi Yossi
b'Rabbi Yehuda lo ka'amar ela de'etz*. Right, there's a whole debate whether
you could make a כלי שרת *kli shareis* out of wood. Whether
the מנורה *menorah* initially was out of wood or whatever. Even he
only allows wood. אבל דחרס לא *aval de'cheres lo*. But everybody agrees
that pottery is too, like, sort of mundane of a material for
a כלי שרת *kli shareis*. And based on the verse that we
learn it out from the מנורה *menorah* etc. so there's a question
whether it has to be metal or can it even be wood,
but everybody agrees that a כלי שרת *kli shareis* is not allowed
to be out of pottery. And that's why. So now we have
concluded that in theory pottery can be כשר kashering... *kashered*. And the
only reason that we don't in general is we don't trust you
to do a good job, to put the fire on the inside.
Ovens that the fire's on the inside can be כשר *kashered*. And
the only reason and number one and number two, the whole rituals
here by the breaking and the scalding or whatever are rooted in
absorption. And therefore in principle כשר *kashering* should work for the כלי
חרס *kli cheres* in the מקדש Mikdash. *mikdash*. It's not just a
ritual, it's a ritual rooted in absorption and in כשר *kashering*. And
for just practical reasons we don't do this with the כלי חרס
*kli cheres* in the מקדש Mikdash, *mikdash*. Yes, Michael?
But the שתי הלחם ולחם הפנים *shtei halechem v'lechem hapanim*, I don't
understand. I mean, if you're not putting in water, you have to
put I'm not putting in oil, I put in water. You still
have to mix it in something.
Right. It's not yeah, I don't know.
Right, it's not that it's like physically impossible. You could like put
it in a כלי שרת *kli shareis* with the water ahead of
time. But for whatever reason, I don't have a full answer to
that, okay? But why it wouldn't be possible. In theory it is
possible. But למעשה lemayseh *lema'aseh* that was the oven was the כלי
שרת *kli shareis* for it. Yes?
You could absolutely כשר *kasher* pottery by putting it back in a
kiln. But typically pottery is painted and while the pottery itself will
do fine in the kiln, right, whatever's on the outside is going
to be destroyed.
Which I guess is helpful in getting back to why the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says we don't trust you to do a good job
because you'll be afraid you'll destroy it. Yeah, I was actually asked
the question just the other day about חרס *cheres* and about pottery
which is like, okay, you can't כשר *kasher* because you can't get
the taste out, but why don't you just go ahead and like
you know, cook it in bleach? And then the bleach will go
into the walls of the pot and it'll be פוגם *pogem* any
taste in it. And then why isn't that enough? So it's like,
okay, that was a good question. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara,
*Gemara* says like this, okay, now. Now the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* continues.
רב יצחק בר יהודה הוי רגיל קמיה דרמי בר חמא *Rav Yitzchak
bar Yehuda havei ragil kamei de'Rami bar Chama*. He has a great
little story. רב יצחק בר יהודה *Rav Yitzchak bar Yehuda* usually would
be spent most of his time in front of רמי בר חמא
Rami bar Hama *Rami bar Chama*. שבקיה *shavkieh*,
but then he decided like, nah, I need a different רבי *Rebbe*.
So he left רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* ואזל ליה לקמיה
דרב ששת *v'azal lei lekamei de'Rav Sheshet*. And he went to רב
ששת Rav Sheshet, *Rav Sheshet* to learn by רב ששת Rav Sheshet,
*Rav Sheshet*. יומא חד פגע ביה *yoma chad paga bei*. So one
day רמי בר חמא *Rami bar Chama* bumped into his ex תלמיד
*talmid*, former תלמיד *talmid*, רב יצחק *Rav Yitzchak*. Okay, אמר ליה amar
lei, *amar lei*: אלקפטה נקטת ריחא אתי ליד *alakpeta naktat reicha ati
leyad*?
So this is apparently some common statement which is that, you know,
basically you went to a רש"י *Rashi* says an officer, or I
think the tax collector, I saw that שטיינזלץ *Steinsaltz* said. And you
think that because you like shake hands with an important person, you're
going to some of their nice smell is going to rub off
on you? So you're like you're going to some other rabbi for
the status
purpose and what, you didn't like
Maybe you went to him because he's more
חשיב. Okay, anyway, so he said אמר ליה, amar lei, no, לאו
משום הכי. lav mishum hachi. No, no, I didn't leave him for
that reason, I didn't leave him because of חשיבות. chashivus. What?
I didn't leave you.
Right, I'm saying I wouldn't go to him, I didn't leave you
for that reason, לאו משום הכי, lav mishum hachi, but what it
actually had to do with, I was concerned about my education. So
מר, mar, which is not what a teacher wants to
hear, מר כי בעינא
מילתא מינך, Mar ki baina milta minach, when I asked a question
from you, פשטת לי מסברא. pashat li misvara. You said, oh, מסברא,
misvara, you gave me a logical or good logical answer, but you
didn't base it on any text.
And they suggest of him when I inquire of him, although it's
not in the text but...
No, no, no, I think you're jumping to the next line. Okay,
let's keep on reading. Okay, let's keep on reading. Some sort? Yeah,
yeah, yeah. Okay. So when I asked you a question, you would
give me an answer based on some, you know, reasoned out position,
but not based on a text. And then
כי משכחת מתנייתא, ki mashkacha masnisa, but then I would show you
a ברייתא braita that would prove you wrong, ופרכא לך, uparcha lach,
and that would contradict what you said, so your logic might have
been brilliant. But they suggest of him. Well, let me just finish
this then you tell me what they... Okay, anyway, and then I
would give you, you know, I would, you would give me some
logic, I would show you a contradiction, ופרכא לך, uparcha lach, and
that would contradict you. Okay, and then that would be the end
of the conversation. So that doesn't help me that you just סתם
stam say things from סברא, svara, in the end I don't wind
up with some real fact. Right, exactly. When not just a counter
סברא, svara, I actually have a counter text. Okay, if it's a
counter סברא svara you could maybe persuade me why your סברא svara
is better, but at the end of the day, סברא svara is
all nice and fine but if there's a text that contradicts, a
text contradicts. But רב ששת, Rav Sheshes. but when it comes to
רב ששת, Rav Sheshes, כי בעינא מילתא מיניה, ki baina milta minei,
when I ask him a question, פשט לי ממתנייתא. pashat li mimasnisa.
He has a text to produce. He shows me a ברייתא braita
to support his position. דכי נמי משכחת מתנייתא, de-ki nami mashkachat masnisa,
then and that, you know what, if you've got a text, even
if I find a counter text, ופרכא, u-parcha, and that contradicts his
text, מתנייתא ומתנייתא היא, masnisa umasnisa hi, it doesn't completely reject his
position because fine, then I have two competing texts and then he
can tell me, I'll tell you why I favor my ברייתא braita
over that ברייתא. braita. Or at best it'll be a draw. But
at least what he told me won't be... it doesn't run the
risk of being completely rejected. Everything you tell me runs the risk
and in the sense you got, didn't just run the risk, maybe
there was a high likelihood, a high occurrence of the things you
told me wound up getting rejected because I had counter texts. He
tells me things based on texts. So even if I have counter
texts, his things are still legitimate and you know, and then maybe
that's where you throw in a סברא, svara, there maybe his סברא
svara could convince me, I'm adding this, it's not in the גמרא,
Gemara but anyway, why his text is better than my text. I'd
much rather go to him, there at least I wind up with
something firm under my belt. With you I'd never know if I
can trust it all because there might just be some contradictory text.
That's not what your English says?
It was confusing. Okay fine. It's using he-he-said-he-said, sir. He was actually
talking as you suggested.
Yeah, yeah, fine. Okay.
So he's only saying this now and not before, you know, maybe
we can work something out, I'll believe you.
You know what, people are like... you can't teach an old dog
new tricks. People are like, you know, set in their ways. And
now we're going to have a very humorous story as this continues.
So let's keep on going. אמר ליה, amar lei, so רמי בר
חמא said, yeah, he says בעי מיני מילתא, bai minei milta, go
ahead, ask me anything, דאפשט לך de-afshat lach and I will deduct
it for you, from סברא. svara. Okay, you're right, that's what I
do, I figure out things from סברא, svara, but כי מתנייתא, ki
masnisa, we'll find out that my סברא svara will be supported by
a ברייתא. braita. It'll be just like something we'll find in a
ברייתא. braita. Yes, I'm going to learn it out from סברא. svara.
Your problem is you need a text, don't worry, we'll find a
text. Okay, בעי מיניה, bai minei, he asked from him, בישול במקצת
כלי, bishul bimiktzas kli, טעון מריקה ושטיפה או אין טעון? taun merika
ushtifa o ein taun? Let's say I cooked, you know, in a
pot, and it only in the bottom inch of the pot. When
I go ahead and I have to kasher the pot, this is
not a normal pot, this is like again for the case like
a חטאת, chatas like the case in the תורה. Torah. Okay, if
I go ahead and the תורה Torah says I have to do
a scalding and a rinsing, it's whatever, I cooked this חטאת, chatas.
do I have to do it just at the bottom of the
pot or do I have to do it with the whole pot?
It's a good question. It didn't exactly say. Okay, so okay, that's
the question. Okay, what's the הלכה? halacha Okay, so that's his question.
So או אין טעון, o ein taun, אמר ליה, אינו טעון. eino
taun. It doesn't have, you only need to do the bottom of
the pot in this case of the חטאת chatas. whatever,
you don't have to
do the whole pot. That's reasoning. That's good reasoning. He's not saying
I'm going to stop using my סברה. sevara. He's just saying I'm
going to show you that I can figure out things from סברה
sevara and in the end they will be supported by a ברייתא.
beraisa. So he says והלו תנא הכי. vehalu tanna hachi. So wait
one minute, where's the ברייתא beraisa to support it? Okay, there's no
ברייתא beraisa that supports that. You're just סתם stam saying it from
סברה. sevara. אמר ליה מסתברא, amar lei mistavra, again from סברה. sevara.
And it makes sense. כבגד. kebeged. מה בגד אינו טעון כיבוס אלא
מקום דם, ma beged eino taun kibus ella mekom dam, the same
way by a garment, which is just elaborating what he said a
minute ago, you only do it where the blood is, אף כלי
אינו טעון מריקה ושטיפה אלא מקום בישול. af kli eino taun merika
ushtifa ella mekom bishul. Here too by the חטאת chatas and the
pot or whatever, the ritual as applies only to the place of
the scalding and the rinsing, only to the place where it was
cooked. So that's again not exactly a ברייתא beraisa unless what he
says is based on my סברה, sevara, it is anchored in a
תנאי tannai source because it's anchored in the משנה. mishna. The same
thing the משנה mishna says about blood, my סברה sevara will bridge
the gap from that משנה mishna to our case. So in the
end it is somewhat anchored in a source. אמר ליה מי דמי.
amar lei mi dami. Since when is it comparable? דם לא מפעפע.
dam lo mefapeia. Blood doesn't spread throughout the garment. So of course
you only have to do it where the blood is. בישול מפעפע.
bishul mefapeia. If you cook, even if you cooked at the bottom,
the taste spreads throughout the whole pot. And therefore even
purely, forget text, purely on a logical basis, your comparison, your, you
know, is, can be challenged. Okay, even logically, yes, I understand your
analog, but it's not a precise analog because since when you cook
stuff in a pot, the taste spreads throughout the pot. Okay, there's
a reason to think that actually you would have to כשר the
whole pot. That's just using סברה. sevara. And not only that, I
got a text. Okay? והא תניא, veha tanya, we taught a text.
Okay, you got a text.
Why is he asking the question?
I let you see how he answers. He asks if you want
to convince me to come back to you, you challenge me, you
ask me something, let's see how you do on this on this.
We got a ברייתא. beraisa. חומר בהזאה ממריקה ושטיפה וחומר במריקה ושטיפה
מהזאה. chomer bahaza mimeryka ushtifa vechomer bimerika ushtifa mehaza. The stringencies of
the blood cleansing over the מריקה ושטיפה merika ushtifa of the pot,
and there's stringencies the other way. חומר בהזאה שהזאה ישנה בחטאת החיצונה
ובחטאת הפנימית. chomer bahaza shehaza yeshna bechatas hachitzona uvechatas hapnimit. The blood
הלכה halacha applies even on an inner חטאת. chatas. Okay?
And the מריקה ושטיפה merika ushtifa does not because מריקה ושטיפה merika
ushtifa is only on something that you eat, and you don't eat
an inner חטאת. chatat, It's only when you cook something, the meat
that you eat. וישנה לפני זריקה. veyeshna lifnei zerika. And also the
הלכה halacha of the blood applies if you'll remember before the blood
has been put on the מזבח. mizbeach. מה שאין כן במריקה ושטיפה.
ma shein ken bemerika ushtifa. Not by מריקה ושטיפה. merika ushtifa. מריקה
ושטיפה merika ushtifa is only meat that can be eaten. It's only
the outer חטאת chatat. and it therefore is only on blood after
the blood has been put on the מזבח. mizbeach. That's when the
meat can be eaten. Okay?
חומר במריקה ושטיפה. chomer bimerika ushtifa. Now מריקה ושטיפה merika ushtifa is
more weighty. שמריקה ושטיפה נוהגת בין בקדשי קדשים בין בקדשים קלים. shemerika
ushtifa noheget bein bekodshei kodashim bein bekodashim kalim. It's not limited to
a חטאת. chatat. It extends even to קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. It's
not even limited to קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. It even applies to
קדשים קלים. kodashim kalim. So it applies to a much bigger scope
of קרבנות. korbanot. And not only that, here's also how מריקה ושטיפה
merika ushtifa is stricter. בישל במקצת הכלי טעון מריקה ושטיפה כל הכלי.
bishal bemiktzas hakli taun merika ushtifa kol hakli. If you do, if
you cook in part of a pot, you have to do מריקה
ושטיפה merika ushtifa on the whole pot. Okay? So it's like an
explicit ברייתא beraisa that shows you that you're wrong. This is a
perfect illustration of why I left you for רב ששת. Rav Sheshes.
You used your סברה, sevara, you claimed your סברה sevara was anchored
in a משנה. mishna. At the end of the day, number one,
your סברה sevara could be challenged. And number two, there's an explicit
ברייתא beraisa that shows you that you're wrong. מה שאין כן בהזאה.
ma shein ken bahaza. אמר ליה אי תניא תניא. ei tanya tanya.
Fine, you got a ברייתא, beraisa, you got a ברייתא. beraisa. Which
is like classic, this is classically why he left. He's like, I'm
going to give you a whole wonderful סברה. sevara. I say, but
I got a ברייתא. beraisa. He says, okay, you got a ברייתא.
beraisa. What can I do? You got a ברייתא. beraisa. I still
like my סברה. sevara. You got a ברייתא, beraisa, you got a
ברייתא. beraisa. Okay? Which basically, it's a phrase that actually is like
a begrudging concession, you know? Because it's still is coming from somebody
who is more in a world of just סברה, sevara, and you
know, and therefore look, at the end of the day if you
have to concede to a text, you concede to a text. It
doesn't mean that that's your orientation to be looking for all the
texts. Your orientation is still to figure things out from סברה. sevara.
If you have to backtrack a few times because you've got some
contradictory text, then you'll backtrack. Okay? But now you see this is
exactly why he left him to go to רב ששת, to go
to, to go to רב פפא, Rav Pappa, right? No, it was
no to go to רב ששת. Okay? וטעמא מאי? vetaama mai? Now
טאקע, taka, what is the reason why you have to do it?
So what do you mean? We just gave a good reason, that
it spreads throughout the whole כלי, right? But we can even give
a reason interestingly, maybe consistent with the idea of like we're here
showing a preference for text over סברה, sevara, rather than just giving
the reason of like oh because when you cook it spreads, we're
going to give a reason that's, meaning we're going to give a
basis on a פסוק, pasuk, by a verse. אמר קרא. amar kra.
The verse says, ואם בכלי נחושת בושלה, veim bekli nechoshes bushala, if
it was cooked in a כלי, ואפילו במקצת כלי, veafilu bemiktzas kli,
in somehow, I don't know how in means even in. part of
it, but that's בכלי, bikli, somehow means even part of the vessel
you have to go ahead and cook the whole thing. So even
when it comes to giving a סברא, sevara, we're not giving a
logical סברא, sevara, which we could have given, we could have said
it spreads throughout, but in the end the סברא sevara we gave
really was just a basis in a verse. Okay, so it's a
great little dynamic here which is like, yeah, now we see exactly
why I left you, because you think, eh, don't worry, I'll show
my stuff will be consistent with all the ברייתות, baraitas, I'll find
a supporting ברייתא, baraita, and in the end you didn't, in the
end it was directly contradicted by it. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara. says like
this. אחד קדשי קדשים, echad kodshei kodashim, whether it's קדשי קדשים kodshei
kodashim or קדשים קלים, kodshim kalim, now we're going to get to
this idea, which is that we as opposed to the blood which
is only by a חטאת, chatat. this applies to all קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay, so, and then רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon I think says not
by... רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says not by קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim.
תנו רבנן: Tanu rabbanan: חטאת. chatat It says, speaks about if you
cook from a חטאת. chatat, אין לי אלא חטאת. Ein li ela
chatat. I only know a חטאת. chatat כל קדשים מניין? Kol kodshim
minayin? How do I know to include other קדשים kodshim to this
הלכה halacha, about cooking in a pot? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: קודש
קדשים היא. kodesh kodashim hi. Okay, because at the end of that
verse says, it is holy of holies. Okay, so meaning it's sort
of broadening the point here that it's not just about a חטאת
chatat when it speaks about the cooking in the pot.
יכול שאני מרבה את התרומה? Yachol shani marbeh et ha-trumah? now of
course that would say you should limit it to קדשי קדשים. kodshei
kodashim. How do you know קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim? We'll see in
a minute. Anyway, maybe therefore I'll include... maybe I'll go so far
to include תרומה? trumah? תלמוד לומר: Talmud lomar: the verse says אותה.
otah. Okay, it says יאכל אותה, yochal otah, will eat it, which
is a limiting thing, which means it's not everything. It ends by
תרומה, trumah, it ends by... it doesn't go further than קרבנות. korbonos,
פרט
לתרומה. Prat le-trumah. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrei Rabbi Yehuda. That's what רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי שמעון אומר: Rabbi Shimon omer: קודש קדשים
היא... kodesh kodashim hi... no, it says קודש קדשים היא, kodesh kodashim
hi, so only the holy of holies. קדשים קלים Kodshim kalim אין
טעונין מריקה ושפיפה. ein te'unin merika u-shefifa. Not קדשים קלים kodshim kalim
like our שלמים. shlamim. דכתיב קודש קדשים. De-ksiv kodesh kodashim. קדשי קדשים
Kodshei kodashim in, קדשים קלים kodshim kalim lo. That's a very reasonable
position of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. מאי טעמיה דרבי יהודה? Mai ta'amei
de-Rabbi Yehuda? So why does רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda extend it to
קדשים קלים? kodshim kalim? So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda will tell you:
מכדי דאצטריך אותה למיעוטי תרומה, mi-di-it-trich otah le-ma'utei trumah, if all it
applied to was קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, you wouldn't need אותה. otah.
You'd say קודש קדשים היא, kodesh kodashim hi, and I would know
קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim yes, קדשים קלים kodshim kalim no. So what's
אותה otah doing? Why do you need אותה otah to limit? So
the fact that you need אותה otah to limit shows me that
קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim is not limited to קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim.
If it was literal, then you wouldn't need a limiting word. And
it means that קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim I should read in an
expansive way to include all things that are holy. And then אותה
otah comes and says: wait, wait, not everything, not תרומה. trumah. So
what I sort of... you know, so what I get in between
the אותה otah exclusion of תרומה trumah and the literal meaning of
קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim is קדשים קלים. kodshim kalim. But if קודש
קדשים kodesh kodashim was literal, I wouldn't need the אותה. otah. The
fact that I need the אותה otah tells me that קודש קדשים
kodesh kodashim is broader. Okay, and אותה otah draws a line. So
אותה otah draws a line at תרומה, trumah, but the broader aspect
of קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim is to include שלמים, shlamim, is to
include
קדשים
קלים. kodshim kalim. Okay, so one minute... מכלל דקודש קדשים טעוני מריקה
ושפיפה, mi-klal de-kodesh kodashim te'uni merika u-shefifa, that shows me that קדשים
קלים kodshim kalim is included. רבי שמעון אמר לך: Rabbi Shimon amar
lach: רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would tell you, אותה כי דאמרינן. otah
ki-d'amrinan. No, אותה otah we learned for an earlier הלכה, halacha you
might remember that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon used אותה otah to tell
me the idea that what do you call it, that
even a... this הלכה halacha about the blood of a חטאת, chatat.
right, that it doesn't apply to when a חטאת chatat, that had
a שעת כושר, sha'at koshir, it didn't have a שעת כושר, sha'at
koshir, you might remember we had that discussion earlier, right, about what
types of חטאות hata'ot are excluded, even one that was פסול pasul
even after it had a שעת כושר sha'at hakosher is excluded based
on the אותה. otah. So he uses this אותה otah not for
the whole cooking context where it appears, but for the earlier verse
which was about the blood of the חטאת to exclude certain חטאות
hata'ot from this הלכה halacha. of the blood of the חטאת. Okay,
so that's what it's functioning for him. ותרומה לא בעיין, Ve-trumah lo
ba'yan, and therefore אותה otah is not coming for saying something here,
it's saying something about the blood of the חטאת, and obviously תרומה
trumah is excluded because it's only about קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. So
therefore it's only about קדשי קדשים. kodshei kodashim. קדשים קלים Kodshim kalim
and תרומה trumah are equally excluded.
Okay, now... now the גמרא continues.
כי דאמרינן, ki-d'amrinan, period. I'm sorry, I put the period in the
wrong place. כי דאמרינן, ki-d'amrinan, period. Now the גמרא continues. ותרומה לא
בעיא שטיפה ומריקה? Ve-trumah lo ba'ya shtifa u-merika? Now are you telling
me that because they both agree that this does not apply to
תרומה, trumah, so are you telling me that תרומה trumah does not
need the שטיפה shtifa and מריקה? merika? How could that be? שטיפה
shtifa again is the sort of scalding and the
rinsing, והתניא בברייתא. ve-ha tanyan be-braita. And now we're going to turn
to a general כשרות, kashring, pot absorption הלכה. halacha קדירה שבישל בה
בשר לא יבשל בה חלב. Kederah she-bishal ba basar lo yevushal ba
chalav. If you cooked meat in a pot, don't use it for
milk. Great ABCs of a kosher kitchen. ואם בישל בנותן טעם. Ve-im
bishal be-noten ta'am. If you used your meat pot for cooking milk,
then does it treif up the milk? It depends, is there enough
meat flavor that it could give טעם ta'am into the milk? Okay,
and there's a whole way we compute that, one in sixty and
so on. תרומה, Trumah, if you used your pot for cooking תרומה,
trumah, לא יבשל בה חולין. lo yevushal ba chullin. Don't cook non-תרומה
trumah in it. Okay, if you don't want your non-תרומה, trumah, your
חולין, chullin, to become
תרומה. trumah. ואם בישל בנותן טעם. Ve-im bishal be-noten ta'am. Now that
won't טרייף treif it up, but it might mean that you'll have
to get a כהן kohen to eat it, but if the תרומה
truma taste absorbed in the pot now goes into, you know, the
stew that you're cooking and you can taste the תרומה truma taste,
and how exactly you determine that again, one in sixty, etc., etc.
Anyway, then, one minute, hold on, then your stew is a problem
and you would only allow a כהן kohen to eat it. So
anyway, the גמרא question is, you see that when you cook תרומה
truma in a pot, you actually,
it gets absorbed, and it could impact the stuff you're going to
cook afterwards. So what do you mean when you say the פסוקים
psukim are only talking about קרבנות, korbonot, they're not talking about תרומה,
truma, but and when you have a תרומה truma in a pot
you don't need to do this ritual, but you do need to
do this ritual; if you don't do this ritual when you cook
תרומה truma in a pot, it can get, it can impact stuff
you're going to cook in it. Okay, which is really another way
of saying, how is what you do by the pot in the
מקדש Mikdash, of the scalding and the rinsing different than any כשר
you would do at home for any pot that absorbed taste that
you don't want, whether it's טרייף, treif, whether it's מילכיג, milchig, whether
it's whatever, you always have to כשר pots. So what's your point
of saying, no, no, the ritual in the תורה Torah only applies
to, you know, to
קודש קדשים kodesh kodashim etc., or קדשים קלים kodshim kalim and it
doesn't apply to other things? But you gotta כשר anything, so what's
the significance of saying whether it's in the ritual in the פסוקים
psukim or not in the ritual of the פסוקים? psukim? So let's
see what the גמרא answer is,
so,
so, wait a minute, אמר אביי לא צריכא אלא דאמר מר בשל
במקצת כלי טעון מריקה ושטיפה כל הכלי התרומה לא צריך אלא מקום
בשול. Amar Abaye lo tzricha ela d'amar mar bishal b'miktzas kli taun
merika v'shtifa kol hakli ha truma lo tzarich ela makom bishal. And
this is wild, what אביי Abaye says is, here's the way the
ritual is different than the normal הלכות halachos of כשר. Normal הלכות
halachos of כשר, you would not have to do the entire vessel,
you could just do the part that you cooked it. So in
theory, if you went ahead and this pot I've used, here it
is, here's my soup pot, okay, that I use for פליישיגס, fleishigs,
okay, and then, and then somebody came and he did a little
bit of, well whatever, let's, no, let's just start with this. Here's
this brand new pot that I bought, my soup pot, and I,
and first time I used it, I used it for פליישיגס fleishigs
down here and the chicken soup only went to that level. Okay,
and now I realize, darn, I wanted to make it a מילכיג
milchig pot, so I have to כשר it. So normally what would
you tell me to do to כשר it? You would normally tell
me fill it up, wait twenty-four hours, fill it up, put it
on hot water blah, blah, blah. אביי Abaye is saying is actually
you could just fill it up up to this point with water
and כשר it. And that the same way it went in that
way, and presumably the logic is, and this gets back to the
גמרא point about don't you need to do the whole thing because
it spreads, but presumably the logic is, if this spread throughout when
you cooked it, then if you cook water here, it'll spread throughout
and it'll just reverse the process. Okay, so even if it's true
that it spreads, just do the same thing you did to get
it in and that'll get it out. So the הלכה halacha that
we said a minute ago that you need to do the whole
pot, that's a special ritual by, you know, קרבנות, korbonos. the whole
pot. Normal כשר only requires you go til the level of how
far the thing got. Now in practice of course we don't say
that, in practice we say you gotta fill the whole thing up,
we even say that it's gotta be, you know, overblow because maybe
things overblew, okay, we also say that you've got to get it
to the point of boiling even if I've only ever used this
to 150 degrees, when I cook it I gotta get it to
212, right, that's boiling, did I remember that from high school science?
Anyway, because we always want you to do the extremes to make
sure you're covering your bases, but what אביי Abaye says in principle
actually you could כשר just by going to the level of use.
The ritual demands that you do it to the whole pot. Okay,
so that's point number one of how the ritual is different from
כשר. Number two, אמר
רבא לא צריכא אלא דאמר מר במים. Amar Rava lo tzricha ela
d'amar mar b'mayim. It says because when it says about מריקה ושטיפה
במים merika v'shtifa b'mayim that the ritual is water, so you have
to דוקא davka use water. Okay, במים ולא ביין, b'mayim v'lo b'yayin,
you can't כשר with, you can't do the ritual with wine in
the מקדש. Mikdash, במים ולא במזוג, b'mayim v'lo b'mazug, you can't even
do mixed wine.
הא, Ha, but if you're going to כשר a pot, אפילו ביין
ואפילו במזוג, afilu b'yayin v'afilu b'mazug, you can use other liquids to
כשר a pot, it doesn't have to be water. So I bet
you didn't know that, but if you wanted to כשר a pot
you could use some, I mean why you would, it would be
a waste of some good stew or some good wine, but in
theory כשר doesn't require water, okay, you can use other liquids. The
ritual requires water. So what's now special about the ritual? Right now
the ritual here in the מקדש, Mikdash, the ritual of the מקדש,
Mikdash well first of all it has to be done in the
מקדש, Mikdash okay, but that's because you're dealing with קרבנות. But besides
which, okay, it has to be filled,
okay, כל הכלי, kol hakli, and it's only water. And the actual
כשר... can be, in theory it can be only up to the
place it was used and could be other liquids. Now by the
way, the fact that kashering can be other liquids, there's actually a
good question, I think it's already in the רשב"א Rashba which is:
Here I was. I cooked chicken soup in this pot, okay? Then
yesterday,
that's two days ago. Today I cooked vegetable soup. After I cooked
vegetable soup, I went ahead and I cooked milk in this pot,
or whatever.
Oh wow, yeah.
So, why is the milk not kosher? Or let's say I cooked
the chicken soup earlier today, okay? I cooked chicken soup at
9:00 AM, that gets to the whole question about whether you have
to wait 24 hours before kashering, but let's bracket that for a
moment. I cooked chicken soup at 9:00 AM, at 10:00 AM I
cooked vegetable soup, at 11:00 AM I cooked milk. So you could
say, you know what? The milk is kosher. Why? Because the vegetable
soup was a kashering the pot. The vegetable soup is just like
water. I kashered it with vegetable soup. So that's actually an issue
that gets discussed להלכה lehalacha about whether that works, because it's only
here that you דוקא davka need water, okay? Here you have to
fill it, we למעשה lemayseh fill it. You here you need water,
of course we למעשה use water, but in principle neither of those
are required by normal kashering. Let's do the third thing, okay? רבה
בר עולא אמר לא צריכא אלא לדאמר מר, Rabbah bar Ulla amar
lo tzricha ela ledamar mar, you need it for what we taught,
מריקה ושטיפה בצונן merika u'shtifa b'tzonen that מריקה ושטיפה merika u'shtifa is
two types, I've been translating it as scalding and rinsing, but we're
going to see there's one opinion, it's coming up in the משנה
Mishna that it is two forms of cold water, okay? Two rinses
of water, we'll see how they're different. But obviously so the first
thing you do is you kasher with a scalding, that isn't even
mentioned. The ritual in the תורה Torah is two מריקה ושטיפה merika
u'shtifa is two other rinsings of cold water. הא אפילו בחמין, ha
afilu b'chamin, but when you kasher you just use hot water and
you don't need it to follow rinsings of water, okay?
So the גמרא says הניחא למאן דאמר מריקה ושטיפה בצונן, hani'cha l'man
d'amar merika u'shtifa b'tzonen, that's if you say they're both cold. אלא
למאן דאמר מריקה בחמין ושטיפה בצונן, ela l'man d'amar merika b'chamin v'shtifa
b'tzonen, but if the מריקה merika is the hot water and the
שטיפה shtifa is the cold water, so both of them have hot
water. So the answer is fine, both of them start with hot
water, but איכא למימר שטיפה יתירתא. ika l'meimar shtifa yetirta. No, at
least the ritual requires a cold rinse, okay? So that is not
by kashering, okay?
So cold rinse, the cold rinse after is only real now is
really only a הלכה by the ritual in the מקדש, all right?
Though and but kashering in theory you just do the hot water.
Now למעשה a ritual developed, a מנהג minhag developed in the time
of the ראשונים Rishonim that when we kasher pots we also put
them in cold water after we're done. I don't know if you
ever was in one of those big פסח Pesach kasherings but they
put them in the boiling thing and then they put them in
cold water, and that's probably patterned after this. So actually what we
do in practice when we kasher is we do do all these
three things as a practice. We fill it, we use water, we
do a rinse after, but in principle these are only rituals that
apply in the מקדש and they're not really needed for kashering, okay?
So this was a very nice little way of highlighting what is
unique
about the מקדש ritual that's not just about kashering. Okay, let's just
read the משנה Mishna and we'll end with that for today. רבי
טרפון אומר בישל מתחילת הרגל יבשל בו כל הרגל. Rabbi Tarfon omer
bishal mi'techilat ha'regel yevashel bo kol ha'regel. If you started a pot
cooking with it at the beginning of a רגל regel like פסח
or whatever, you don't have to do the rinsing and the scalding
or if it's a pottery pot you don't have to break it
every day, you can just keep on using it throughout the רגל,
regel, okay? Because there's just so much meat or whatever, somehow that
means that you don't have to it doesn't get נותר notar and
you don't have to break it, we'll see what that is in
the גמרא, okay? Or scald it. וחכמים אומרים עד זמן אכילה. Vachachamim
omrim ad zman achila. No, I don't care if it's the רגל
regel or not the רגל. regel. Once the time of eating of
the meat is over then the pot has to be processed in
whatever way, you know, either the scalding or the or the breaking.
Okay, מריקה ושטיפה. merika u'shtifa. Now when you get to the מריקה
ושטיפה, merika u'shtifa, מריקה כמריקת הכוס, merika k'merikat ha'kos, מריקה merika is
like you would rinse out
a כוס, kos, these are both כוס, kos, meaning you're rinsing out
on the inside, ושטיפה כשטיפת הכוס, u'shtifa k'shtifat ha'kos, like a rinsing
it out on the outside. So according to this they're both, okay,
ומריקה ושטיפה בצונן u'merika u'shtifa b'tzonen and they're both cold water, so
this is what we referred to beforehand. There would be a hot
process beforehand to kasher it, a scalding water, but these according to
this משנה Mishna they both refer to a cold process, a cold
water, one is on the inside, one is on the outside, rinse
it on the inside, rinse it on the outside, it's both cold
water. השפוד. Hashapud. Now if you have a what do you call
it, a spit
והאסכלא ve'ha'askala or a grill, so that would be directly over a
fire, מגעילן ברותחין. magilan b'rotchin. So there בחמין. b'chamin. So there you
do הגעלה, hagala, now
the first use of the word הגעלה. hagala. הגעלה hagala is a
kashering word, okay? So it's quite fascinating because I was throwing in
before when we mentioned מריקה ושטיפה, merika u'shtifa, I was throwing in
it was preceded by a kashering process, but that hadn't been mentioned,
right? I mean we just did it right before in the גמרא
comparing it to koshering, saying why it's more than koshering. Okay, but
anyway here the גמרא finally when it was talking about מריקה Merikah
and שטיפה Shtifah didn't hint at the idea that there was a
koshering that took place. Here when it talks about the spit and
the and the grill, it doesn't mention מריקה Merikah and שטיפה, Shtifah,
it doesn't mention the ritual, it uses the verb of מגעילן, Magilan,
okay, מגעילן Magilan which is הגעלה, Hagala, which is how you kosher,
means immerse it in hot water, okay? So you immerse it in
hot water. So number one, it's interesting the shift to talking about
language of koshering. Number two, what's interesting is this is stuff that
goes directly over the fire, and we normally assume that stuff that
goes directly over the fire, right, you need to
actually kosher it by directly placing it over the fire. Why is
immersing in hot water sufficient? Okay, so we will end with this
tantalizing mystery and pick up with this גמרא. Yes. Two questions.
One, back to the תרומה Terumah pot that you